An Inventory of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection Records
Hoover Institution Archives
- Follow-up conferences--State, county, and city (Box 62)
  - States
    - Virginia
      - Requests for charters and other conference materials, 1934-1939. (Folder 75: 5)
      - Correspondence, 1931-1934 and undated. (Folder 75: 6)
        Lists of persons registered at November conference, medical conferences, and residents of Virginia invited to both November and February conferences; remarks on community responsibility for child care; speech by Ray Lyman Wilbur; report on the findings of the governor's conference on childhood and youth; and telegram
      - State information, 1930-1935 and undated. (Folder 75: 7)
        Correspondence; health survey of Virginia's children; lists of state officers, medical conferences, members registered at November conference, and Board of Directors of Cooperative Education Association; printed matter; report; and speech by Ray Lyman Wilbur
    - Washington (Box 76)
      - Requests for charters and other conference materials, 1933-1940. (Folder 76: 1)
      - Correspondence, 1931-1934 and undated. (Folder 76: 2-3)
        Includes lists of Planning Committee members, members of Section III, Education and Training, and medical conference attendees; memoranda; minutes of meeting; note; program; statistical data; telegram; and miscellany
      - Congress of Parents and Teachers, 1931-1932. (Folder 76: 4)
    - West Virginia--Correspondence, 1931-1934. (Folder 76: 5)
      Includes clipping, extract of address by George Hastings, manual for workers on the West Virginia White House conference, memoranda, printed matter, telegram, and miscellany
    - Wisconsin--Correspondence, 1931-1932 and undated. (Folder 76: 6)
      Includes brochure; bulletin; clipping; lists of medical conferences, persons registered to attend the November and February conferences, and state officers; note; statistical data; and telegram
    - Wyoming (Box 77)
      - Correspondence, 1930-1934. (Folder 77: 1-2)
        Includes clipping; conference proceedings; data on Wyoming birth and mortality rates for children; data on the Division of Education and Training; lists of officers and members of the continuation committee, registrants at November and February conferences, and state officers; memoranda; note; printed matter; proclamations of May Day and National Child Health Day; and telegram
      - State information, 1932-1934. (Folder 77: 3)
        Brochure, bulletin, clippings, correspondence, lists of state officers and registrants at the November conference, press release, printed matter, and report
- Expense statements, vouchers, and receipts, 1928-1931 (Box 78-89)
- Publications (Box 90)
  - Correspondence
    - November conference, 1930. (Folder 90: 1)
      Relates to the selection of editors of the conference reports
    - Selection of preliminary reports, 1930 (Folder 90: 2)
    - Children's Charter. Notes, printed matter, and telegrams
      - Samples and prices, 1931 (Folder 90: 3)
      - Styling and printing--Norman T. A. Munder & Company, 1930-1932 (Folder 90: 4)
      - Garamond Press Incorporated, 1931-1933 (Folder 90: 5)
    - Copyright permissions on materials from conference reports, 1931-1954 (Folder 90: 6)
    - Staff members--Evelyn Dewey, Katherine Glover, Ethel Minder, and Ellen McBryde, 1933-1936 (Folder 90: 7)
    - H. E. Bernard, Inez G. Richardson, M. Van Rensellaer, and others, 1931-1932 and undated. (Box-folder 91: 1)
      Includes memoranda, printed matter, and telegrams
    - Katherine Glover and George A. Hastings, 1931-1932 and undated. (Folder 91: 2)
      Includes memoranda
    - Katherine Glover and Ray Lyman Wilbur, 1931-1933. (Folder 91: 3)
      Includes other related materials
    - Katherine Glover and others, regarding medical service, 1931-1932. (Folder 91: 4)
    - Style and policies, 1931-1932 (Folder 91: 5)
    - Progress reports on printing and editing., 1932-1933. (Folder 91: 6)
      Includes list of published reports, memoranda, note, statement of unpublished conference reports, royalty statement, and related materials
    - Staff members.
      - New York and California (Stanford), 1932-1934 (Folder 91: 7)
      - New York and Washington, D.C.
        - 1931-1932 (Folder 91: 8)
        - 1931 (Box-folder 92: 1)
    - Petty cash and salary orders--New York office, 1931-1932. (Folder 92: 2)
      Includes, lease agreement, and memoranda
    - Circular promotional mailings, 1931 and undated. (Folder 92: 3)
    - Promotion through state and provincial library extension agencies, 1931-1932. (Folder 92: 4)
      Includes newsletter and printed matter
    - Magazine and newspaper promotion--A-Z, 1931-1932 and undated. (Folder 92: 5)
      Includes clippings, memoranda, statement, and telegrams
    - Follow-up Committee on Medical Service, Section I, regarding combined volume on dentistry, 1931 (Folder 92: 6)
    - Faegre pamphlets series--Growth, personality, and habits, 1931-1932. (Folder 92: 7)
      Printed matter, reports, and telegram
    - Editorial preparation of program material--Winifred Moses, 1931. (Box-folder 93: 1)
    - Combined report on Negro child life, 1929-1933. (Folder 93: 2)
      Includes note and printed matter
  - "Report to the Committee on Child Dependency as Affected by Racial Factors--Negro Group," Section IVC-1, Socially Handicapped-Dependency and Neglect, 1930 (Folder 93: 3)
  - "The Negro Child," manuscript for a monograph by Forrester B. Washington--Collection of reports prepared by committees and subcommittees of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, undated. (Folder 93: 4)
    Includes a note by Inez G. Richardson, 1962
  - Official Directory of the National Association of Colored Women, 1926-1928, undated (Folder 93: 5)
  - "Negro Family Life," by Ernest R. Groves--Report of Section III, Committee A, Subcommittee Number 3, 1930 (Folder 93: 6)
  - Report of the Subcommittee on the Negro School Child, Committee on the School Child, Section IIIC, undated (Folder 93: 7)
  - Report on Social and Economic Factors in Housing for Negroes, Division of Social and Economic Factors, Committee on Negro Housing, Part I, 1931 (Folder 93: 8)
  - Correspondence
    - Nutrition pamphlets, 1931-1932. (Box-folder 94: 1)
      Includes article and manuscript on nutrition, printed matter, program, telegram, and tentative outline for nutrition series
    - "The Rural Child"--Excerpts from the White House conference reports, 1931 and undated (Folder 94: 2)
- November conference--Washington, D.C.
  - Volunteer workers--Invitations issued, 1929-1930. (Folder 94: 3)
  - Program Development, 1930 and undated. (Folder 94: 4)
    Correspondence, list of groups interested in listening to the president's address, memoranda, notes for Executive Committee discussion, schedule, and related materials
  - General session, Constitution Hall, 1930. (Folder 94: 5)
    Correspondence, memoranda, program, and schedule
  - Luncheons and dinners, 1930. (Folder 94: 6-7)
    Announcement, correspondence, financial records, schedule of luncheons, and telegrams
  - Materials distributed to delegates, 1930 and undated. (Folder 94: 8)
    Address of Herbert Hoover, chart, preliminary statement, program, and miscellany
  - Meeting rooms, 1930. (Folder 94: 9)
    Correspondence, lease agreement for Constitution Hall, and 1 photographic print depicting an empty conference room, undated
  - Complete set of abstracts of committee reports, 1930. (Box-folder 95: 1)
  - Travel certification, 1930. (Folder 95: 2)
    Correspondence, certificates for reduced fares, memoranda, and printed matter
  - Stenotype service--Master Reporting Company, Inc., 1930. (Folder 95: 3)
  - Pledges from different organizations supporting conference objectives, 1930. (Folder 95: 4)
    Correspondence and resolution adopted by the Convention of the National League of Women Voters
  - Sampling of mail showing range of interest and effectiveness of conference work, 1931. (Folder 95: 5)
    Brochures, bulletin and summary of conference proceedings, clipping, correspondence, printed matter including copy of Children's Charter, journal, statement prepared for public release, and telegram
  - Congressional replies to letters transmitting gifts, 1931. (Folder 95: 6)
  - Governor's conference regarding gift of Children's Charter, 1931. (Folder 95: 7)
  - Trade Associations--Acknowledgements of offers of cooperation, 1931. (Folder 95: 8)
    Correspondence and list of convention dates
  - Miscellaneous papers from the November conference, 1930. (Box-folder 96: 1)
    Carbon copies of steno transcripts
  - Proceedings of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, vol. I and II, Washington, D.C., 1930 November 19-22 (Folder 96: 2-3)
  - Official proceedings--General session and Sections II-IV, 1930. (Box-folder 97: 1)
  - Children's Charter
    - Editorial preparation, 1930-1931. (Folder 97: 2)
      Correspondence, memoranda, note, and miscellany
    - Materials from Ray Lyman Wilbur's file, 1932. (Folder 97: 3)
      Analysis of point I, correspondence, introduction to the report, and note
    - Point by point analysis, 1930-1933. (Folder 97: 4-6)
      Article clippings, correspondence, note, press release, printed matter, telegram, and related materials
    - Thirty-five copies of the Children's Charter analysis, 1931 (Box-folder 98: 1)
    - Analysis and copies of President Hoover's letter, 1931. (Folder 98: 2)
      Correspondence, notes, and analysis of the Charter
    - "Our Challenge"--Children's Charter playlet, 1932-1936. (Folder 98: 3)
      Copy of the playlet, and correspondence
    - The Children's Charter--Programs and articles, 1938-1943. (Folder 98: 4)
      Brochures, correspondence, note, printed matter, and program
    - Miscellany, undated (Folder 98: 5)
    - Posters--Children's Charter series, 1931 (Folder 98: 6)
  - White House conference proceedings--November and February sessions, The United States Daily, 1930. (Box-folder 99: 1)
- February conference sessions
  - Medical Service
    - General, 1930-1931. (Folder 99: 2)
      Address, clippings, correspondence, and telegrams
    - Proceedings of the joint sessions, White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, 1931 (Folder 99: 3)
    - Proceedings of the Follow-up Committee, Washington, D.C., 1931 (Folder 99: 4)
    - Medical conference arrangements and preliminary statement, 1931 and undated. (Folder 99: 5)
      Correspondence, press release, printed matter, program, schedule, and miscellany
    - Medical conference--Railroad, 1930-1931. (Folder 99: 6)
      Certificate, correspondence, printed matter, and telegram
- White House Conference on Children in a Democracy (Box 100)
  - General, 1939-1942. (Folder 100: 1)
    Address, article, brochure, clippings, communiqué from the child welfare front, correspondence, newsletter, printed matter, program, schedule of meetings, and miscellany
  - Papers and discussions at the initial session, 1939 April 26; "A Children's Charter in Wartime," 1940; general reports adopted by the conference, 1940 January 18-20; recommendations, 1940 January 18-20; preliminary statements, 1940 January 18-20; the follow-up program, 1940 July; "Community Projects for Child Welfare," undated; and "Standards of Child Health, Education, and Social Welfare,", 1942 (Folder 100: 2-3)
  - Printed matter
    - Proceedings of the Care of Dependent Children, 1909; Minimum Standards for Child Welfare and Standards of Child Welfare--Report, 1919; and Child Care and Child Welfare, 1921 (Folder 100: 4)
    - Directory of Local Child-Health Agencies in the United States, 1922; In Behalf of Mothers and Children: The Story of the U.S. Children's Bureau, 1930; and miscellany, 1919-1921 (Folder 100: 5)
- White House Conference on Children and Youth, 1948-1951 and undated. (Box-folder 101: 1)
  Bulletin, copy of "A Charter of the Rights of the Child," memoranda, press release, printed matter, and report
- Organizations
  - American Child Hygiene Association, 1909-1924. (Folder 101: 2)
    Brochure, index of transactions, minutes of annual meeting, printed matter, program, and report
  - Child Health Organization of America, 1918-1922 and undated. (Folder 101: 3)
    Announcements, correspondence, minutes of semi annual meeting and report, program, and telegram
  - American Child Health Association, 1925-1938 and undated. (Folder 101: 4)
    Announcement, brochure, chart, correspondence, magazine, minutes of meetings, printed matter, and reports
  - Handbook of Social Resources of the United States, 1921 (Folder 101: 5)
  - American Association for Study and Prevention of Infant Mortality--Proceedings of the sixth annual meeting, 1915 and directory of children's hospital, 1928 (Folder 101: 6)
  - American Child Health Association (A.C.H.A.)--Dissolution of Association (Box 102)
    - Special membership meeting, 1935 August 13
      - List of members to whom notice of meeting was sent with affidavit of mailing; list of all members entitled to vote and signed proxies returned; copy of minutes of meeting; and copy of letters from Shattuck, Bangs, and Davis, stating they have received from the secretary of state of West Virginia, his certificate of dissolution of A.C.H.A. (Folder 102: 1)
      - Letters to members, 1935 July 9. (Folder 102: 2-4)
        Includes notice of meeting, follow-up letter regarding proxies, publicity notice; and letters from members expressing regret of dissolution
    - Miscellaneous materials for home and school distribution, 1918-1933 and undated (Box-folder 103: 1-3)
  - Committee on School Child (Box 104)
    - Report of the Subcommittee on Health Education in Secondary Schools, Section III, undated (Folder 104: 1)
    - Report of the Subcommittee on Co-operation of Home with School, Section IIIC, undated (Folder 104: 2)
    - Report of the Subcommittee on Mental Hygiene in Schools, Section IIIC, undated (Folder 104: 3)
  - American Child Health Association (A.C.H.A.)
    - Newspaper and radio releases
      - "What the Doctor Says"--Weekly newspaper columns
        - Series I, numbers. 1-52, 1932 February - 1933 February (Box-folder 105: 1)
        - Series II, numbers. 1-52, 1933 February - 1934 February (Folder 105: 2)
        - Series III, numbers. 1-52, 1934 February - 1935 February (Folder 105: 3)
        - Series IV, numbers. 1-21, 1935 February - July (Folder 105: 4)
    - Radio talks on child health and protection, 1933-1935 (Folder 105: 5)
    - Printed matter
      - Health in Play: A Guide for all who Help Children in their Play, 1924 (Folder 105: 6)
      - Signs of Health in Childhood, 1934 (Folder 105: 7)
    - Miscellany, 1931 and undated. (Folder 105: 8)
      Chart, leaflets on emergency nutrition and food at low cost, and poster
  - American Relief Administration affiliated with American Child Health Association--Child Health News, 1923 March 15 (Folder 105: 9)
  - Child Health Organization of America--Many Roads to Health, 1922 (Folder 105: 10)
  - American Child Health Association (A.C.H.A.) (Box 106)
    - Radio talks
      - On the reports of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, undated (Folder 106: 1)
      - On the Children's Charter, undated (Folder 106: 2)
    - Clippings, 1927-1932 (Folder 106: 3)
    - Professional studies, 1924-1935. (Folder 106: 4)
      Includes letters and related materials
    - Magazine releases--White House conference sent by American Child Health Association (A.C.H.A.), 1930 and undated. (Box-folder 107: 1)
      Article, press releases, radio announcements, and talks
    - Materials relating to the proposed declaration of May Day
      - Clippings, letter from President Herbert Hoover proposing May Day, note, printed matter, and miscellany, 1924-1925 (Folder 107: 2)
      - Brochures, bulletin, President Herbert Hoover's letter, press release, printed matter, report, and miscellany, 1925 (Folder 107: 3)
      - Bulletin, letter, printed matter, and report, 1926-1928 (Folder 107: 4)
    - Herbert Hoover
      - Article and statement about Herbert Hoover, 1925 and undated (Folder 107: 5)
      - 6 photographic prints depicting Herbert Hoover as honorary president of the American Child Health Association, 1929-1930 (Folder 107: 6)
      - Child Health Bulletin and radio talks, 1929-1930 (Folder 107: 7)
      - Publication and promotion--New York Times and New York Herald Tribune, 1931 (Folder 107: 8)
      - "Yea, I have a Goodwill Heritage"—Title of 1 photographic print of Eugenics, American Eugenics Society, undated (Folder 107: 9)
      - Child Health Councils, 1932 and undated. (Folder 107: 10)
        Statements relating to developments of state councils and materials relating to the Massachusetts plan
    - Minutes of meetings
      - Third annual meeting, Atlantic City, New Jersey, 1926--Volume II Part I and Part III, and Volume III Part II (Folder 107: 11)
      - Fourth annual meeting, Washington, D.C., 1927 May 9-11 (Folder 107: 12)
    - Printed matter, 1926-1935. (Folder 107: 13)
      "Advancing the Cause of Child Health"—-Fourth annual report of the general executive of the American Child Health Association presented at the annual meeting of the association, New York City, 1926 October 15; Child Welfare Magazine, 1927; "Five Years of the American Child Health Association: A Bird's-Eye View," 1927; and The Story of the American Child Health Association, 1935
- Report of Committee on Undergraduate Teaching of Obstetrics, undated (Box-folder 108: 1)
- Report of the Committee on Prenatal and Maternal Care
  - Section IB, Medical Service, Subcommittee IA, Obstetric Education of Physicians (Graduate Education), undated (Folder 108: 2)
  - Section I, Medical Service, Subcommittee IB on Obstetric Teaching and Education of Nurses and Nursing Attendants, undated (Folder 108: 3)
  - Section IB, Medical Service, Subcommittee on Education of the Laity and Social Workers, undated (Folder 108: 4)
  - Section IB, Medical Service, Subcommittee III on Interested Organizations, undated (Folder 108: 5)
- Committee on Milk Production and Control, report of Subcommittee IV (Economic Aspects) of Section IIC, undated (Folder 108: 6)
- Public Health Organization--Report of Section II Committee A, E. L. Bishop, chairman, 1930 (Folder 108: 7)
- Preliminary report of the Committee on the Economic Aspects of Milk, 1931 (Folder 108: 8)
- Reports of the Subcommittee on Dental Service in Schools, Section III (Education and Training), F. J. Kelly, chairman; and Section IIIC, Committee on the School Child, Thomas D. Wood, chairman, 1932 and undated (Folder 108: 9)
- Financial records, 1930-1932 and undated. (Box-folder 109: 1-8)
  Includes correspondence and notes
- American Child Health Association (A.C.H.A.) (Box 110)
  - Certificate of incorporation, 1923. (Folder 110: 1)
  - May Day--Child Health Day, 1924. (Folder 110: 2)
    Includes an article, "An Awakening Conscience," undated
  - Ray Lyman Wilbur, 1923-1924. (Folder 110: 3)
    Correspondence relating to his participation in A.C.H.A. Includes minutes of meetings, printed matter, report, telegram, and miscellany
  - The Story of the American Child Health Association, 1935 (Folder 110: 4)
  - Certificate of registration covering the name, "Child Health Bulletin," as a trademark for periodicals, 1929 (Folder 110: 5)
  - Gold medal awarded to the American Child Health Association, Brussels, Belgium, 1928 (Folder 110: 6)
- Child Health Organization of America--Certificate of incorporation and by-laws, 1921 and undated (Folder 110: 7)
- American Child Hygiene Association--Certificate of incorporation, undated (Folder 110: 8)
- Raymond H. Sawtelle--Financial records (Box 111)
  - 1930-1931. (Folder 111: 1)
  - 1931-1932. (Folder 111: 2)
    Includes letters
  - 1932-1940. (Folder 111: 3)
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, and telegram
  - 1933-1936. (Folder 111: 4)
    Includes correspondence with Inez G. Richardson and Ray Lyman Wilbur, memoranda, minutes of meetings, and reports
  - Agreement between the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection and the Century Company, and power of attorney, 1933 and undated. (Folder 111: 5)
  - The Century Company, 1932-1936. (Folder 111: 6)
    Bills and statements
  - Correspondence between the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection and Century Company, 1932-1942. (Folder 111: 7)
- Duplicate deposit slips, 1932 (Box 112)
- Reconciliation of bank account, 1933 April
- Purchase records, 1930-1936.
  Books and literature
- Check records and summaries, 1929 July - 1931 April
- Sales records, 1932 May - October. (Box 113)
- Check records, 1932 January - June
- Statements on literature sales and collections after closing of central office in 1933 February.
  Includes duplicate deposit slips and national net book and collection deposits
- Cancelled checks, 1930-1932 (Box 114)
- Cancelled checks, 1929-1930. (Box 115)
  Includes first checkbook used by White House Conference on Child Health and Protection before regular checks were printed, 1929. Includes deposit slips
- Conference on Care and Protection of Children (Box 116)
  - Committee on Growth and Development, 1930 and undated. (Folder 116: 1)
    Correspondence and summary of materials relating to Sections I and II of the Committee
  - Committee on Medical Care for Children, 1930 and undated. (Folder 116: 2)
    Letters and forms
  - Committee on the School Child, 1930 and undated. (Folder 116: 3)
    Correspondence, list of members, and program
  - Abstract of the report of the Committee on the Infant and Preschool Child, undated (Folder 116: 4)
  - Follow-up Committee, 1931. (Folder 116: 5)
    Correspondence, minutes of meeting, report, and related materials
  - Cancelled checks, 1930-1932
  - Follow-up Committee of Section I, 1931-1932 and undated. (Box-folder 117: 1)
    Correspondence, manual for conduct of infant and youth child health conference, records of resolutions adopted by the Massachusetts Committee of the American Academy of Pediatrics, and related materials
- White House Conference Committee on the School Child, Washington, D.C., undated. (Folder 117: 2)
  Preliminary reports
- Conference on Care and Protection of Children
  - Organization and procedure, 1929. (Folder 117: 3)
  - General, 1929-1930. (Folder 117: 4)
    Clipping, comment, correspondence, financial records, memoranda, and telegram
  - Children's Charter, undated. (Folder 117: 5)
    Index and remarks
  - Character study of childhood, 1931. (Folder 117: 6)
  - Miscellany, 1929 and undated. (Folder 117: 7)
    Growth and Development Committee--Correspondence and related materials
- Report of the proceedings of meeting of Subsection A, Family and Parent Education, Section III, Education and Training,1929; list of members of Planning Committee, 1929; and outline of work to be done by each subcommittee, undated (Folder 117: 8)
- Printed matter, 1929-1931 and undated. (Folder 117: 9)
  Includes "The New Children," article by Ray Lyman Wilbur
  - Questionnaire, 1929 (Folder 117: 10)
- American Child Health Association, 1930. (Folder 117: 11)
  Minutes of meeting and report
- Lists of personnel from various committees and subcommittees, undated (Box 118)
- Clippings and printed matter (Box 119)
  - A Survey of Day Nurseries, 1931. (Folder 119: 1)
  - Education for Home and Family Life, Part II: In Colleges, Section IIIA--Report of the Subcommittee on Prenatal Education, 1932 (Folder 119: 2)
  - The Administration of the School Health Program, Section IIIC--Report of the Subcommittee, 1932 (Folder 119: 3)
  - Official proceedings, 1930 (Folder 119: 4)
  - Brochures relating to differences in children, developmental responsibility, family, cooperation between home and school, and other related matters, undated (Folder 119: 5-10)